Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
My Lady,
I can no longer be in your service.
What happened? Calm yourself down.
The Household Department just came to deliver a message.
Concubine Beauté has specially requested me to work in her palace.
I see.
It's not bad for you to serve Her Highness Concubine Beauté.
You may pack and leave right away.
Thank you, My Lady.
I really wish I could stay.
After I leave, please take care of your health.
Jade,
call everyone in.
Yes.
I have been sick for almost two months already.
I prefer a quiet healing environment
and my palace is overstaffed for that.
I've summoned all of you to ask one question only:
If anyone wishes to leave the Palace of Pearl Jade,
you may take a sycee from Jade and leave.
We all should congratulate Mr. Kang and Mr. Yin
on their new positions with Concubine Beauté.
They will pack and leave today.
My Lady has treated you kindly, Mr. Kang,
and you have been as loyal as a dog.
But when you see a higher branch to jump to,
you can forget about your mistress, can't you?
Vermilion, you misunderstood.
I only have the heart to serve My Lady,
but Concubine Beauté asked for me.
I cannot be where my heart wants to be.
Your heart?
I never knew that you could force a cow to drink
by pressing its head.
Since you are devoted to serving My Lady,
your loyalty must not be compromised.
Why don't you decline and tell Her Highness that
a loyal servant won't serve two masters?
I'm sure Concubine Beauté will understand.
And I will apologize to you over tea.
I'm afraid your mouth doesn't say what your heart wants to.
Vermilion.
Mr. Kang has great loyalty.
It doesn't matter who he serves.
Jade, give him the sycee.
Farewell, Mr. Kang.
And you too, Mr. Yin.
You must learn from your shifu's loyalty.
It goes a long way.
Thank you, My Lady.
Go with them if you wish!
While you can still get the money.
If you make a request after today,
My Lady will send you to the Department of Penalty.
Don't think twice!
I'm afraid I am incompetent to serve you, My Lady.
My Lady, I am willing to follow you without a second thought.
Me as well, My Lady.
I am indebted to your favors, My Lady.
I'd never dare to betray you.
Why is that?
When my brother was desperately sick,
you sent Dr. Wen to treat him.
Without you, my brother wouldn't still be alive.
We owe you a great debt.
I will spare no effort in my service.
If I can't pay you back in this life,
I will become a black ox that takes you to the Pure Land.
Stop it.
I mean every word I say.
I would never lie to My Lady.
Enough of the bows.
If you break your forehead,
I will have to ask Dr. Wen to help you again.
I do not want the outsiders to keep saying that
everyone in my palace is weak and sick.
It's been cold at night.
Xiao-Yunzi is always freezing on guard.
Prepare a thicker blanket for him.
Yes.
Thank you, My Lady.
All of your days have not been easy,
following an unwell and neglected concubine.
But you still treat me well.
I don't know how I can repay your kindness.
For as long as I live,
I won't let your days be difficult.
Thank you, My Lady.
The Household Department is so dismissive.
Because of My Lady's status, they didn't send good charcoal.
Not so loud.
My Lady is unwell.
She will feel worse if she hears it.
Is the water boiling?
Yes.
This charcoal is smoky.
I'm afraid we can't use it indoors.
I'll go fill a hot water bottle for My Lady to keep her bed warm.
Aye, go ahead.
Peace to My Ladies.
It's very cold these days,
the perfect weather for Attendant Sourire to sleep more.
Peace to Lady Shen and Companion An.
It's freezing in here.
- Are you feeling better?
- Meizhuang.
- Sourire.
- Lingrong.
- Your hands are cold.
- Have you been better?
Just the same.
You can't go on like this.
I like the color of your hairpin.
It must be a gift from His Majesty.
Meizhuang is in high favor now.
Your palace is secluded,
and the cold makes it even less suitable for recuperation.
I brought you several baskets of silver charcoal.
It should last for a while.
I saw Jinxi was burning dark charcoal.
The Household Department must be giving you trouble.
I have to report this to the Empress.
Inconsideration is natural for a favorless concubine.
Let's save ourselves from one more trouble.
Because you're in favor, they don't dare neglect me too much.
Besides, you two have already brought me some charcoal.
Nothing can compare to the kindness
of sending charcoal on a snowy day.
It's because you have a tolerant mind.
You even put up with that heartless Kang Luhai.
When a heartless person is out of sight,
he's out of my mind.
What do you mean?
The loyalty of the servants outweighs the number.
Indeed, I will be careful about mine as well.
And you too, Lingrong.
Thank you for your reminder.
I will learn to manage my servants.
Sourire is having a slow recovery
probably because of her troubled mind.
I'm all right. What about you?
Have you served His Majesty?
Why would His Majesty even remember me?
Don't overthink.
With the warfare in the Northwest,
it's natural that His Majesty overlooks the harem.
You will serve His Majesty sooner or later.
I understand. I heard that His Majesty
has not visited the harem for over ten days.
Yes, the Empress Dowager will be chattering if she finds out.
In this weather, I know you'll be using hot water bottles.
I made this cover overnight
so your hands wouldn't get burned.
This flower-patterned textile was our welcome gift
when entering the palace.
Isn't it a pity to have it made into a cover?
Not at all.
I don't have anything presentable.
It's worthwhile if you like it.
I do.
The new year is near,
so the Empress sent me to check the decorations in the harem.
I have to go now.
Of course, be careful when you walk.
I will also leave and visit you another day.
You may not be used to the cold.
Don't go outside if you don't have to.
It's all right. I like spending time with you both.
Jinxi, please walk them out.
Yes.
Take care and feel better soon.
My Lady, it's time for your medicine.
How much longer do you have to take this?
After all, any medicine can do some harm to your health.
This formula only slows down my recovery.
There's no need to worry.
Did anyone find out?
Just Vermilion and I. No one else knows.
But why would you even hide this from Lady Shen and Companion An?
I see them as my sisters.
That's why it's best they don't know.
There is a chance this may come to light one day.
If that happens, they won't be implicated.
Lunar, you never have to make the trip here.
Please have a seat. Bring a chair quickly.
It's all right.
Lady Shen just had some items sent to Attendant Sourire.
So I stopped by for this month's stipend.
Go pack the stipend for Lady Shen's palace.
Lunar is waiting.
Yes.
You came from the Palace of Pearl Jade?
Yes, Lady Shen and Attendant Sourire
have been friends since childhood.
My Lady has been concerned
ever since Attendant Sourire fell sick.
I hope Attendant Sourire is being taken good care of.
Of course, we all care for someone when they're unwell.
Yet her palace is ill-equipped for the winter.
Fortunately, My Lady has always been sending things to her.
Who knows what would have happened otherwise?
How can we have troubled Lady Shen about this?
This is the negligence of our department.
I will... I'll have things made right in no time.
Thank you for taking your time.
It must be an omission of your staff.
Aiyo, what wind carried you here, Madam Songzhi?
Don't butter me up.
The New Year is approaching.
Our palace is short on gold wrapping paper.
Her Highness may need to prepare gifts.
So I came to get some in advance.
You should have told me earlier.
We sent golden paper to your palace before anyone else's,
and doubled the amount for you.
The Empress's palace just collected one stack.
I'm afraid we have to share the remaining gold paper
among the other concubines.
Huang Guiquan,
have you grown tired of your job by now?
The requests from my palace
have never been turned down before.
Since you still have gold paper in store,
send it to my palace and replenish some later.
But...
The lower-rank concubines don't deserve
to wrap gifts in gold paper.
Don't you agree?
- Here you go.
- Thank you, sir.
Oh!
You are picking up this month's stipend?
Congratulations.
Perhaps I misremembered the date.
I thought Lady Shen was still forfeiting her stipend.
Huang Guiquan, I've said what I said.
If we run out, don't blame Her Highness for her temper.
Aiyo, what a job it is.
- I'm frozen to the bone.
- Did you get everyone's year-end rewards?
Yes.
All thanks to Noble Lady Shen,
the Household Department gave us the amount in full.
It's fortunate we have Lady Shen.
She also just had a lot more gifts sent here.
Did she?
Now we can celebrate the New Year happily.
Isn't today the 25th already?
I wonder if My Lady can get well enough
to attend the imperial banquet on New Year's Eve.
Don't worry.
Jiang Fuhai just came to announce the Empress's edict
that My Lady is allowed to rest in her palace.
She doesn't need to attend the banquet on New Year's Eve.
Isn't that great? We can see in the New Year together.
Exactly.
His Majesty and Her Majesty arrive.
Peace and auspicious fortune to Your Majesties.
This is a family dinner. Don't stand on ceremony.
Have a seat.
I thank Your Majesty.
Imperial brother, you always tell us to ignore the rules.
(Yunli, Noble Prince Guo)
But no one listens or ever forgets the rules.
Only my seventeenth brother would say that.
He never stands on ceremony.
He's not absent or even late today.
That is a surprise.
How can I be late for the New Year reunion?
I raise my cup to my imperial brother.
I wish Your Majesty and the Great Qing peace and prosperity.
Cheers!
May Your Majesty live in eternal happiness and longevity.
May Your Majesty reign for ten thousand years,
and ten thousand of ten thousand years.
Drink up!
This is fine wine.
Consort Fleur,
did you drink it up?
Of course I did.
Your Majesty is in a good mood today.
News of victory came from the Northwest this afternoon.
Nian Gengyao quelled Luobu Zangdan's rebellion in Qinghai.
All the tribes and their livestock were captured in full.
What a general he is!
What a capable Great General!
Congratulations, Your Majesty.
Congratulations! Your Majesty can be at peace now.
Your brother did an excellent job.
My brother renders good service on the front line,
and I will do my best in the harem.
It's our duty.
Our courtyard would have been perfect
if it had some plum and cypress trees.
It looks brown and bare on a winter day.
My Lady, if you want to liven up our palace,
We can put paper-cuts onto the windows.
They'll bring a festive air.
Great idea! Can you bring some colored paper and gold foil?
We'll make paper-cuts.
Yay! I'll go get the paper.
I'll go get scissors.
I'll look for paper-cutting patterns.
I'll go with you!
Come on.
🏮Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组🏮
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Your Highness, Consort Honnête's palace reported
that she is having a seizure and requests to see a doctor.
Today is New Year's Eve, and she'd bring back luck.
Request denied.
What if she sends for a doctor herself?
Tell the Imperial Infirmary
if anyone dares to treat that wretch,
they are standing in the way of Nian Shilan.
Yes, Your Highness. I take my leave.
This is to Your Majesties.
Where is Attendant Sourire?
Attendant Sourire is still unwell.
I told her to stay in on such a freezing night.
Jinxi, let me have a look.
The peacock you cut is so full of life.
- So beautiful!
- Indeed.
It cannot compare to the Two Gods of Harmony you made.
Look, it's as if they were coming to life.
Exactly.
These figures are from the fables.
I don't know what they look like.
But I heard some people can cut out
the portrait of a person with paper.
Sadly, I've never seen it.
My Lady, one of those people
is standing right before you.
I saw Xiao-Yunzi making a portrait of you.
He's hiding it in his sleeve.
- Really?
- Don't... talk nonsense.
Xiao-Yunzi, don't be shy.
Let me see it.
Let us see.
It looks just like you.
Xiao-Yunzi, you have gifted hands.
He does.
Not at all, it doesn't do justice to your beautiful face.
I'll make a better one next time.
It does resemble My Lady a lot.
But on the eyes and brows,
it also looks like Jade.
How can I compare to My Lady?
Come here.
Jade does look like me after living together all these years.
But why don't I look like you?
Wouldn't it be scary if everyone looked the same?
But you take after my playful nature.
I heard about this tradition in the palace.
On New Year's Eve, you can make a wish by hanging
your favorite thing on a tree. The taller the better!
My Lady, if you like this portrait,
why not put it onto a tall tree in the yard?
You can hope for good fortunes in the coming year.
It will also be a blessing for Xiao-Yunzi.
Good idea.
But there are only bare branches in our yard.
How about we put the portrait on some blooming plum trees?
Wonderful!
The Garden of Leaning Plums is a good place, and close to us.
Are the flowers white in color?
No, they are pink with a jade-white center.
They look like beautiful rosy clouds.
Lovely.
Clouds of red plum against the white snow,
and a floating fragrance.
What a beautiful scene for a memorable night.
I've got to see it!
My Lady, don't go.
My Lady, you shouldn't go out due to your health.
And the Empress instructed that
your condition might spread to others.
We will be held responsible if Her Majesty finds out.
Indeed.
Everyone is at the banquet at this time.
I will wear a cloak to keep myself warm and inconspicuous.
Besides, I've been staying in for so long.
I should go out for a walk.
My Lady...
Do not follow me!
I'll go alone.
Whoever stops me
will be standing on guard outside for the rest of tonight.
My Lady...
Fifth Brother.
- I wish you peace and happiness.
- You too.
Are the plum trees flowering in the palace?
Plum blossoms rising over the frost and snow.
I want to go take a look.
It's freezing cold outside.
Your Majesty should care for your health.
They're rising over the frost and snow.
How can I leave them unnoticed?
Say no more.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
No one is allowed to follow.
I'll take a walk by myself
to sober up.
- But Your Majesty...
- Your Majesty...
I'll be fine.
Your Majesty.
Where is Your Majesty going?
Your Majesty, what shall we do now?
It's dark and slippery outside.
Seventeeth Brother.
His Majesty insisted on going by himself,
but he has to be taken care of on such an icy night.
Why are there red plum flowers today?
Consort Fleur arranged the banquet decorations.
She doesn't know.
Your Majesty need not worry.
I'll follow His Majesty.
(Yu Ying'er)
Why do I have to do this in the cold on New Year's Eve?
Just because I'm new to the palace!
Asking me to cut flowers for the gods...
Everyone in the palace seeks His Majesty's favor.
But I only wish for the good health of my family
and for my life to be peaceful in the harem.
I understand it is difficult to stay outside the incessant rivalries.
“If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers,
spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
Who is there?
Who is there? Who is it?
Answer me or I'll have the entire garden searched!
I am a maid working in the garden.
Please forgive me for disturbing your visit.
Are you educated? What is your name?
I'm afraid my humble name would tarnish your ears.
Don't come over!
My socks are wet, I'm taking them off.
The flowers are just as beautiful as before.
"Alike are the flowers time after time;
Different are the beholders year after year."
Consort Fleur decorated the banquet with plum flowers.
It wasn't intentional.
I was sentimental.
She married into my estate later.
She knows nothing.
It's been years, and Your Majesty still cannot let go?
Can't let go of what?
I'm looking forward to the warm spring weather.
You can come here to talk and play Go with me.
Your Majesty's wish is mine as well.
But for now, I desire a cup of wine
after smelling the inebriating blossoms.
I'll fulfill this delightful wish with you.
Seeking plums in the snow
and returning with delighted hearts.
That deserves three hearty toasts.
There was another pleasure.
I didn't expect to come across a talented maid.
What a nice surprise.
Congratulations, Imperial Brother.
You're back, My Lady.
My Lady.
What is wrong?
Have some tea to warm up.
Are you numb from the cold?
What happened?
I came across two cats jumping at me.
They scared me.
My Lady has always been afraid of cats.
It must have been frightening to see two at once.
I'll make strong ginger soup
to dispel the cold and calm your nerves.
My Lady, many people like to keep cats in the palace.
They have an untamed nature.
You need to be more careful in the future.
Did you make a wish?
I did.
But it was too cold. I came back quickly.
Why did you find your way here?
Please forgive me, Your Majesty.
But I couldn't put my mind at ease
while no one was accompanying Your Majesty.
So I followed Noble Prince Guo quietly.
“The mantis catches the cicada while a siskin follows.”
I only had my eyes on Your Majesty.
It was my fault.
Since you are here, I have a task for you.
I need you to look for a knowledgeable maid
in the Garden of Leaning Plums.
That will make up for your mistake.
Yes, Your Majesty.
But I hope Your Majesty can enlighten my dull mind
how to test the knowledge of the maid.
Ask her what is the next line for
"If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers."
Aye.
They hoped the game of Madiao cards would keep them awake,
but everyone is dozing off now.
I am sleepy as well.
My Lady, your luck was incredible today.
Now we don't have any lucky money for the new year.
It was only because you all went easy on me.
I don't know much about fabric patterns in the palace.
I wanted to ask you about dragon roundels.
Who can wear this pattern in the palace?
Why do you ask, My Lady?
I was just wondering what people would wear for the banquet.
I see, My Lady.
The dragon roundels are not for normal princes.
They are exclusively used by the Emperor
and his most esteemed brothers.
Of the prior emperor's many princes,
who could be invited to the New Year banquet?
Lord V and Lord X.
And Lord XVII.
He is a half-brother of His Majesty,
but they both were brought up by the Empress Dowager.
They are very close.
I've heard of Lord XVII before entering the palace.
He's proficient in the Six Arts and lives "as free as a wild crane".
His flute playing is unrivaled in the capital.
Nine of the princes fought ruthlessly for the throne.
Lord XVII found pleasure in solitude
and that granted him a distinguished life.
That is true.
Those who fight are not always as blessed as those who don't.
That's why you are a blessed one, My Lady.
I surely hope so.
It's late. Sleep well, My Lady.
Per His Majesty's decree, the whole palace
will celebrate the New Year together.
His Majesty has a couplet riddle for everyone.
Any eunuch or maid who can solve it
will be amply rewarded.
Please tell us the riddle, sir.
It will be fun even if we don't know much about riddles.
Listen up, the first line is
"If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers."
Does anyone know the second line?
"Spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
Your mind is elsewhere.
The game is over.
I lost.
My skills are no match for Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, I've completed the task to the best of my ability.
But...
Your Majesty didn't say the answer to the riddle.
Su Peisheng doesn't know the second line.
That must be a difficult job.
If it's not done well,
that's because you lack competence.
May Your Majesty calm your anger.
Your Majesty must be thirsty after the game.
Please have a cup of tea before punishing me.
Is the tea made of the snow on the plum flowers?
It smells of plum blossoms.
I beg Your Majesty's pardon.
That is the smell of my clothes.
I didn't mean to disturb Your Majesty.
Your Majesty certainly has unique attendants.
I will ask my servants to also
soak themselves in the smell of flowers.
I don't remember seeing you before.
When did you start serving here?
"If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers,
spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
I was tending to the flowers in the Garden of Leaning Plums.
Mr. Su pitied my hard work,
and offered me the honor to serve Your Majesty once.
Was it cold walking all the way here?
The wind and snow have stopped.
It's much better than the shoe-drenching night on New Year's Eve.
You did a thoughtful job.
Your Majesty, I shall return to my work in the garden.
The garden is full of plum flowers.
But I need one in my palace.
You may stay here.
I thank Your Majesty.
What is your name?
My humble name is Yu Ying'er.
Yu Ying'er is granted the title of Escort.
She will reside in the Palace of Accumulated Purity.
Yes.
Long live the Emperor!
"Rather than a leisurely return to Heaven’s jade and gold palaces,
I would instead be drunk among the flowering Luoyang plums."
Do you not understand what His Majesty said?
No, I hope Your Lordship can enlighten me.
It is a poem by Li Bai. His Majesty likes Li Bai.
[It's not by Li Bai. He's testing her.]
I thank Your Lordship. I understand now.
I bid Your Lordship goodbye.
Where are you heading to?
I'm going to register the new concubine
with the Household Department and Attendance Services.
His Majesty will reward you for your hard work, sir.
I dare not think of that.
When you deliver something, it's better to take the wrong route
than to hand over the wrong thing.
You can sing Kunqu Opera?
I learned it from my father. He's in a Kunqu troupe.
Your Lordship was saying "to hand over the wrong thing".
Would Your Lordship clarify that for me?
It was just a thought I had. Don't mind it.
A strange thing happened in the palace.
What is it?
His Majesty somehow became fond of
a maid from the Garden of Leaning Plums.
She was first titled Escort,
and has just been promoted to Companion.
From... the Garden of Leaning Plums?
Yes.
It is not uncommon for an emperor to favor a maid.
His Majesty dotes on her.
As much as you?
Almost as much.
I heard that she can sing Kunqu.
That is a novelty.
I would also like a girl who's good at
arranging flowers and singing Kunqu.
But regardless of how favored she is,
with her background she will not surpass you.
I know that.
But Lingrong is not happy about it.
Right.
She has not even served His Majesty yet.
She doesn't mind the other concubines,
but this one has a birth ten times humbler than hers.
It upsets her now that they are at the same rank.
Does Lingrong not want to serve His Majesty and gain more favor?
His Majesty is a rare visitor to the harem.
When he does come,
he only visits Consort Fleur and a few others.
You know how the people treat you in the palace.
You would live worse than a maid
if you aren't favored by His Majesty.
The other concubines might say that.
But you have been continuously favored since arriving.
I'm just concerned now that I've seen others.
What if one day I fall out of favor too?
Not even to mention your intellect and background,
His Majesty's affection for you will not let that happen.
I do hope so.
My Lady, we have gifts for the Lantern Festival.
[the 15th of the first lunar month]
Please go check on them.
I will leave now.
Peace to Noble Lady Shen.
Companion Yu is being courteous.
The roads are wet and slippery.
His Majesty bestowed a sedan
to escort me on my trips.
Please pardon my inconvenience
to greet you on the ground.
You're right.
If you fell, you wouldn't be able to serve His Majesty.
Noble Lady, I came from Consort Fleur's palace
and I'm going pay respects to Her Majesty.
Will you please make way for me?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.